{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One man with this surname published an abolitionist newspaper titled True American. That politician was the cousin of another man of this surname who, in 1816, was made president of the American Colonization Society. That man with this surname served three terms as Speaker of the House, including one in which he made a “corrupt bargain” with John Quincy Adams to sway the election of 1824. For ten points, give the surname of the prominent Kentucky politicians Cassius and Henry.",
      "answer": "Clay A"
    },
    {
      "question": "At this battle, a sudden rainstorm rendered many of the crossbows of Carlo Grimaldi’s contingent unusable. One commander in this battle refused to come to the aid of the Black Prince, saying “let the boy win his spurs” as he resisted an attack in which John the Blind was killed. This defeat for Philip VI led to the capture of Calais. For ten points, name this 1346 battle in which the English longbow was used to great effect against the French.",
      "answer": "Battle of Crecy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader first rose to prominence as mayor of Davao City. After UN criticism of extrajudicial killRings by this leader, he responded by threatening to withdraw his nation from the UN. In September, 2016, this leader expressed a desire to kill as many people as Hitler did in the Holocaust. After his election, this leader launched an all out war on drugs, encouraging the population to kill drug addicts and drug dealers. For ten points, name this President of the Philippines.",
      "answer": "Rodrigo “Rody” Duterte"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a colony, this modern-day state passed the Halifax Resolves, the first document advocating for independence from Britain. The building of the opulent Tryon Palace in this state’s city of New Bern Dsparked the War of the Regulation. Despite heavy losses, Charles Cornwallis led the British to victory over Nathaniel Greene’s forces at a battle in this state. For the point, name this state where the Battle of Guilford Courthouse took place in Greensboro.",
      "answer": "North Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 1930 opera based on a man born in this city had a libretto written by Paul Claudel. That Verdi opera is named for the first doge of this city, Simon Boccanegra. A Darius Milhaud [mee-yohd] opera focusing on a man born in this city uses Spanish themes to symbolize the title character’s departure from Cadiz. For ten points, name this Italian city, the birthplace of the subject of the opera Christophe Colomb.",
      "answer": [
        "Genoa",
        "Genova T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An Aksumite invasion of this city supposedly failed when the lead war elephant refused to enter it. A group of militants led by Juhayman al-Otaybi laid siege to a building in this city in 1979. This city was briefly the capital of the Kingdom of Hejaz after the dissolution of the Ottoman Empire. The Quraysh tribe of this city was defeated in the Battle of the Trench. For ten points, name this city at which the F annual “stoning of the devil” ceremony occurs at the Kaaba.",
      "answer": "Mecca, Saudi Arabia"
    },
    {
      "question": "After his most celebrated invention, this man engaged in a debate over whether a “micro” or “monolithic” version of a program was superior. That debate was between this man and Andrew Tanenbaum. After coming under fire for using BitKeeper this man developed a free version called Git. Red Hat offers a business version of an operating system based around this man’s kernel. For ten points, A name this developer and namesake of the open-source operating system Linux.",
      "answer": "Linus Benedict Torvalds"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ratified version of this agreement included protections for land on which both Peter Hargous and A.G. Sloo planned to build a railroad. That railroad secured in this agreement was never built but had been intended to cross the Isthmus of Tehauntepec. Ownership of the Mesilla Valley was resolved in this agreement which had been left undecided at the earlier negotiations to end the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this American land acquisition agreement with Mexico. R",
      "answer": [
        "Gadsden Purchase",
        "Gadsden Treaty,",
        "Treaty of Mesilla before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1797 a hypnotist from Goa was sent to a prison off the coast of this city where wealthy inhabitants could afford rooms called pistoles which were larger than typical cells. A fort built during the reign of Francis I served as the site of this city’s basilica Notre-Dame de la Garde. Abbe Faria and Edmond Dantes were imprisoned in the Chateau d’If [DEEF] off this city in The Count of Monte Cristo. For ten points, name this city in the south of France in what was once the ancient Greek colony of Massalia.",
      "answer": "Marseille, France D"
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician controversially used the phrase “coffee-house babble” to describe a report of foreign atrocities, but he regardless sent Lord Salisbury to negotiate at the Constantinople Conference. This man, who led the Young England movement after breaking with Robert Peel, signed the Royal Titles Act, conferring the title of “Empress of India” upon Queen Victoria who favored this man more than his liberal rival. For ten points, name this 19th century British prime minister, the rival of William Gladstone.",
      "answer": [
        "Benjamin Disraeli, 1st Earl of Beaconsfield",
        "Earl of Beaconsfield T"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This Native American tribe adopted many colonial children, including Eunice Williams, following the Raid on Deerfield during Queen Anne’s War. One leadFer of these people led a namesake group of Loyalists during the American Revolution known as “Brant’s Volunteers.” Known as the “Keepers of the Eastern Door,” these people are the easternmost member of the Iroquois Confederacy. For ten points, name this tribe for whom a central New York river and valley are named.",
        "answer": [
          "Mohawk",
          "Kanien’keha:ka"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the most noted Mohawk is this co-founder of the Iroquois Confederacy, known as Ayenwathaaa in his native tongue, made famous by Henry Wadsworth Longfellow. A",
        "answer": "Hiawatha"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The final battle of this period, Wavre, failed to affect its outcome as it prevented the troops of Emmanuel de Grouchy from being deployed elsewhere. Though Gebhard von Blucher was shot off his horse at this period’s battle of Ligny, he returned to aid the British during an engagement in a Belgian town. For ten points, identify this period in which Napoleon’s return to power culminated in a defeat at Waterloo, named for its approximate length in the spring and summer of 1815.",
        "answer": [
          "Hundred Days War",
          "War of the Seventh Coalition R"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The beginning of the Hundred Days began on March 20 when Napoleon returned from exile on this Tuscan island.",
        "answer": "Elba"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author won a posthumous Tony Award for Lucky Guy, her story of the police brutality-exposing reporter, Mike McAlary. The first of this author’s three Oscar nominations was for a 1983 biopic about labor activist and whistleblower Karen Silkwood. This writer’s final screenplay was the first major film D adaptation of a blog, fictionalizing Julie Powell’s experiences with cooking. For ten points, name this American filmmaker who wrote Sleepless in Seattle and Julie & Julia.",
        "answer": "Nora Ephron"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Karen Silkwood was played in the 1983 film about her by this actress who has been nominated for more acting Oscars than anyone else. This woman also played author Isak Dinesen in Out of Africa and Margaret Thatcher in 2011’s The Iron Lady",
        "answer": "Meryl Streep T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While a member of SASO, this man presented a paper on “White Racism and Black Consciousness.” Fearing that he would be monitored by police, Unity Movement leader Neville Alexander refused to meet with this man. Five police officers confessed before the Truth and Reconciliation Commission to having tortured this man who coined the phrase “Black is beautiful” in a Pretoria prison. For ten points, name F this founder of the Black Consciousness Movement and anti-Apartheid activist.",
        "answer": [
          "Steve Biko",
          "Bantu Stephen Biko,"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Steve Biko was a member of this Nguni ethnic group whose language is the second most popular home language in South Africa after Zulu.",
        "answer": "amaXhosa A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This writer argued against the Brown v. Board decision in “Court Order Can’t Make the Races Mix.” This writer described living in Eatonville, Florida and studying under Franz Boas in the autobiography Dust Tracks on a Road. Alice Walker revived interest in this writer when she claimed to have found her unmarked grave and wrote an article titled “In Search of,” this writer. For ten points, name this anthropologist, folklorist, and novelist who also wrote Their Eyes Were Watching God.",
        "answer": "Zora Neale Hurston"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hurston studied under Franz Boas while at Barnard College, a woman’s college affiliated with thisRIvy League research university in New York City.",
        "answer": "Columbia University"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s attempt to set up the New Virginia Colony and the Carlota Colony failed. Conservatives hated this man for abolishing child labor, and liberals hated this man for having been installed by foreign powers. This man refused to abandon his followers despite Napoleon III withdrawing his forces but was eventually defeated by Benito Juarez’s forces and executed. For ten points, who was this second and last Emperor of Mexico? D",
        "answer": "Maximilian I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Maximilian was the younger brother of what Austrian Emperor who ruled between 1848 and 1916?",
        "answer": [
          "Franz or Francis Josef I",
          "pronunciations with a “J”",
          "a “Y” sound T"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A possible reference to “Potnia” at this people’s city of Ekron has led to proposals that they were related to the Mycenaeans. The earliest known reference to these people comes from Ramses III’s inscription at Medinet Habu. After the battle of Aphek, these people captured the Ark of the Covenant from the Israelites. In the Book of Judges, Samson destroys many of these people along with their temple F to Dagon. For ten points, name these Canaanites, a major Old Testament enemy of Israel.",
        "answer": "Philistines"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Perhaps the most noted Philistine was this man from Gath, a formidable opponent for the shepherd boy who would become King David.",
        "answer": "Goliath A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician was one of the plaintiffs in the landmark 1976 campaign finance case Buckley v. Valeo. An informal slogan from this man’s hippie supporters suggested they would “Get clean.” This politician’s unexpectedly strong finish in the New Hampshire primary was one factor in Lyndon Johnson’s withdrawal from that race. For ten points, name this Minnesota senator who unsuccessfully ran on an anti-war platform for the 1968 Democratic presidential nomination.",
        "answer": "Eugene McCarthy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Though McCarthy’s anti-war campaign wasn’t expected to do well in the primaries, he won New HamRpshire largely due to public opposition to what offensive in Vietnam that occured just six weeks prior to the March 12 voting in New Hampshire?",
        "answer": "Tet Offensive"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Chickamauga",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President whose brother-in-law, Confederate general Benjamin Hardin Helm, was killed in the battle F",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "State in which the battle took place, later the site of Sherman’s March to the Sea",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union commander whose resilience resulted in the nickname the “Rock of Chickamauga”",
          "answer": "George H. Thomas A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unpopular Confederate commander of the Army of Tennessee, later recalled to Richmond",
          "answer": "Braxton Bragg"
        },
        {
          "question": "November, 1863 Union victory in a city just north of Chickamauga",
          "answer": "Chattanooga Campaign"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union commander and victor at Stone’s River, relieved by Grant after Chickamauga",
          "answer": "William S. Rosecrans R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederate general who served as vice president under Buchanan",
          "answer": "John C. Breckinridge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position where retreating Union forces rallied to create a defensive line around the Snodgrass House",
          "answer": "Horseshoe Ridge D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "David Lloyd George",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Great War” during which he served as prime minister F",
          "answer": [
            "World War One",
            "WW1"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty that he helped negotiate at the Paris Peace Conference",
          "answer": "Treaty of Versailles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party from which he was the last prime minister, originally growing out of the Whigs",
          "answer": "Liberal Party A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Government with which he signed a treaty in 1921 which divided an island into a Free State and a northern portion",
          "answer": [
            "Irish Republic",
            "Ireland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Foreign Secretary who issued a namesake declaration promising a Jewish state",
          "answer": [
            "Arthur Balfour",
            "1st Earl of Balfour"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Government proposal for wealth redistribution sponsored by Lloyd George and Winston Churchill R",
          "answer": "People’s Budget"
        },
        {
          "question": "Annual speech he gave on the state of the British economy while Chancellor of the Exchequer",
          "answer": "Mansion House speech"
        },
        {
          "question": "1922 war scare in which he called for war against Turkey",
          "answer": [
            "Chanak Crisis",
            "Chanak Affair",
            "Chanak Incident D T"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battle of Gallipoli",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First Lord of the Admiralty and future prime minster who resigned after his failure to defeat the F Ottomans",
          "answer": "Winston Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strait connecting the Sea of Marmara with the Aegean that the campaign attempted to force",
          "answer": [
            "Dardanelles",
            "Hellespont"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "European region of Turkey in which Gallipoli is found, named for this ancient, Hellenized historical region A",
          "answer": "East Thrace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military unit composed of soldiers from Australia and New Zealand",
          "answer": [
            "ANZAC",
            "Australia New Zealand Army Corps"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Weapon laid in fields that sank British and French battleships",
          "answer": [
            "Naval mine",
            "equivalents to “Naval” 6RGerman military adviser who commanded the defense of Gallipoli ANSWER: Otto Liman von Sanders",
            "either Liman",
            "von Sanders"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British commander who was replaced by Charles Munro after failing to defeat the Ottomans",
          "answer": "Ian Hamilton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final British attempt to break the stalemate, which led to the replacement of Frederick Stopford",
          "answer": "Landing at Suvla Bay D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one phase of this battle, 200 sailors were killed when a bomb pierced the armor of the USS Princeton. The USS Darter successfully sFunk the Atago during an engagement at (20 pts)",
        "Palawan Passage during this battle. A radio silence that prevented Shoji Nishimura from communicating with other admirals allowed Jesse Oldendorf to set a trap during the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Surigao Strait within this larger battle. This battle marked the first use of kamikaze attacks by Japan. For ten points, name this World War Two battle, possibly the largest naval engagement in history."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Leyte Gulf"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Prior to this campaign, German forces were deployed at Hitler’s orders in “Feste Platze,” A [PLET-zeh] fortified towns that were to be held at any cost. The largest single German defeat of the war occurred during this campaign when much of Army Group Centre was surrounded in the (20 pts)",
        "Minsk Pocket. This operation ended after the securing of bridgeheads on the Vistula, as the victors controversially failed to aid the (10 pts)",
        "Warsaw Uprising. For ten points, name this 1944 Soviet operation that recaptured Belarus during World War Two, codenamed for a Russian commander of the Napoleonic Wars."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Operation Bagration",
        "Belorussian Strategic Offensive Operation before “codenamed” R"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Lipona Plantation, just east of this city, was the residence of Prince Achille Murat, a nephew of Napoleon. The Columns, built in 1830, is this city’s oldest building and stands next to the (20 pts)",
        "Leon County Library. This city is the site of an historic reproduction of the Franciscan mission, San Luis de Apalachee. A state university in this city plays football at (10 pts)",
        "Doak Campbell Stadium and was founded in 1851 as a compromise location between Pensacola and Saint Augustine. For ten points, name this city, the largest city in the “Big Bend” and the “Panhandle” of Florida. DANSWER: Tallahassee, Florida (4) This man combined his Confucian and Catholic beliefs to develop a system of government known as Personalism. Cable 243 indicated that foreign forces would not oppose a coup against this man after he had sent secret police to attack the (+) Xa Loi [SAH LOY] Pagoda. During this man’s tenure, he ordered liquid chemicals to be poured on protestors at Hue [HWA]. The monk (*) Thich Quang Duc [TIK KWONG DUK] set himself on fire to protest this man’s rule. For ten points, name this leader of South Vietnam in the early stages of the Vietnam War."
      ],
      "answer": "Ngo Dinh Diem T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This art form takes its name from the Japanese for “floating world,” a description of the hedonistic lifestyle enjoyed by the 17th century Edo merchant class. Van Gogh copied one of these artworks, (20 pts)",
        "Sudden Shower over Atake, during a phase he described as Japonaiserie. This art form declined under the (10 pts)",
        "technological modernization of the Meiji Restoration. For ten F points, name this art form, practiced by Hiroshige and Hokusai and notably used for The Great Wave off Kanagawa, a Japanese form of woodblock printing."
      ],
      "answer": "Ukiyo-e"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One ruler of this name issued the mining code Ius regale montanorum after silver was discovered at Kutna Hora. Drahomira arranged to have Saint (20 pts)",
        "Ludmila, the grandmother A of another ruler of this name, killed at Tetin Castle. That ruler with this name was murdered by his younger brother Boleslav at the feast of Saints Cosmas and Damian. A ruler of the Premyslid [PREM-iss-lid] dynasty with this name is buried in Saint Vitus Cathedral in (10 pts)",
        "Prague. For ten points, give this name of four kings of Bohemia, the first of whom is commemorated in a song for giving alms on the Feast of Stephen."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Wenceslas",
        "Vaclav"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this author’s autobiography, he described suffering shrapnel wounds to the lung duRring the Battle of Somme while a member of the Royal Welsh Fusiliers. In a novel by this author, the title character is advised to love history by his tutor, Athenodorus, and to survive by acting foolish by his idol, (20 pts)",
        "Asinius Pollio. This author of the memoir Goodbye to All That and a noted translation of The Twelve Caesars wrote about a king who refers to himself as “Old King Log” after the execution of his (10 pts)",
        "wife Messalina. For ten points, name this author who wrote about the reigns of Tiberius and Caligula in I, Claudius."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert von Ranke Graves D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this court case, Thomas Addis Emmet and Thomas J. Oakley represented the defendant who had earlier served as the fifth governor of New Jersey. (20 pts)",
        "John Marshall found that the word “among” in Article I, Section 8 of the Constitution was central to the decision of this case, which came about after one state’s Court of Chancery issued an injunction against a company operating out of Elizabethtown. Robert (10 pts)",
        "Livingston and Robert Fulton’s monopoly on New York navigation resulted in, for ten points, what case that established the federal government’s sole ability to decide on matters of interstate commerce?"
      ],
      "answer": "Gibbons v. Ogden T"
    }
  ]
}